next we will look at how the
replacements policy for the cash which
choses if you remember which block to
kick out when we need more wrong
interacts with the hit time of the cash
a simple replacement policy such as
random which randomly picks the block to
replace among those that are in the set
has nothing to update on a cache hit
when we have a cache hit we don't have
to do anything in order to be later able
to do random when we have a Miss that's
when we start implementing our policy by
randomly selecting a block to kick out
this results in faster hits because
there is nothing we need to do for the
replacement policy when we have a hit
and that's nice however the random
policy is not very good for miss rate
because we often kick out blocks that we
will very soon need to use and we don't
like that in contrast least recently
used or LRU results in a lower miss rate
which we like but we have to on every
cache hit update potentially a lot of
counters even if we don't update and we
have to look at them so there is a lot
of activity on every cache hit that
results from needing the state that will
later use to select the block we will
kick out and this spends a lot of power
and also results in slower hits to
illustrate what happens on a cache hit
using LRU let's look at the 4-way set
associative cache whose counters are
currently 0 1 2 & 3 if the processor
accesses this line here and has a hit
the new values of the counters are going
to be this one becomes the most recently
used and all of the other counters get
decremented as you can see all of the
counters have changed and this happens
on a cache hit so a cache hit can result
in updating up to n counters where n is
our associativity let's look at what
happens when one of the more recently
used blocks is accessed let's say we
access not the most recent list but the
next one in that case this becomes the
most recently used block the counters
that are larger than this one get
decremented so this becomes 2 and the
smaller than this stay the same
so we get this so only two counters have
changed now but note that even though we
have only changed two counters we had to
actually check for each counter whether
it's lower than this or not so even when
we access the most recently used block
and the counters don't change at all
because this becomes three and counters
larger than it get decremented but there
is nothing larger and this lower then it
stayed the same
we still had to determine that this is
the highest counter anyway so that we
don't decrement anything or we had to
actually check for each of these
countries whether it's lower so one way
or the other even for a hit to the most
recently used block we have to do
something and that again slows down the
hits and spends power so what we want is
a replacement policy that retains the
Miss rate very close to LRU meaning we
want to smartly replace the blocks so
that we kick out the block that is
unlikely to be used soon or the least
likely to be a sone but we want to do
less activity on cache hits to do that